A Finding Aid to the Robert Kipniss papers circa 1932-2023, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Robert Kipniss papers
circa 1932-2023
Archives of American Art
Kipniss, Robert
AAA.kipnrobe
Archival Resource Key
3.2 Linear feet
The papers of painter and printmaker Robert Kipniss measure 3.2 linear feet and date from circa 1932-2023. They illustrate his career through biographical material, correspondence, writings, and printed and photographic material.
Biographical / Historical
Robert Kipniss (1931-) is a painter and printmaker who works mainly in New York.
Kipniss was born in Brooklyn, New York. During his childhood he attended New York's Art Students League when he was sixteen on Saturdays and he began college in 1948, attending Wittenberg College in Springfield, Ohio for two years before transferring to the University of Iowa. After graduating with a B.A. in English Kipniss stayed at the university and earned a Master of Fine Arts degree in 1954. After gaining this degree he, and his former wife Jean, moved to Manhattan and Kipniss was drafted into the United States Army in 1956 where he used his talent to create training aids.
Kipniss has written poetry, published books, and illustrated two volumes of poetry. He is known for his paintings, lithographs, and mezzotints. His early work was with paintings focusing on abstracts, biomorphic forms, landscapes, still lifes, and figures. The lithographs he later created followed this style. Kipniss did not fully focus on mezzotints until 1990 and had his first solo mezzotint show in 1992.
Since 1965 Kipniss has had more than twenty-two museum exhibitions around the world and his work is held by more than eighty-eight museums and institutions.
Kipniss currently maintains a studio on the Hudson River in Westchester County, New York and is married to his second wife Laurie Lisle.
Arrangement
This collection consists of five series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1979-2021 (.1 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1989-2017 (.2 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1954-2017 (.2 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 4: Printed Materials, circa 1952-2023 (1.9 Linear feet: Boxes 1, 2, 4, and 5)
Series 5: Photographic Materials, circa 1932-2007 (.8 Linear feet: Boxes 3, 5, and 6)
Scope and Contents
The Robert Kipniss papers measure 3.2 linear feet and date from circa 1932-2023. Biographical materials consist of Kipniss' CV, awards and honorary degrees, and an interview with WWNO New Orleans in digital format. Correspondence is personal and professional and is to and from Kipniss. Writings include the manuscript of Shine (2017) and Kipniss' thesis, as well as Kipniss' poetry. Printed materials consist of exhibition catalogs, news clippings, and materials about two exhibitions in digital format. Photographic materials consist of photographs of Kipniss, his exhibitions, and his artwork.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records or audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Papers donated in 2013 by Robert Kipniss and in 2024 by Laurie Lisle, Kipniss' spouse.
Scrapbooks; Printmakers -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York
- Biographical Material, circa 1979-2021; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; .1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material includes a CV, an interview of Kipniss for WWNO New Orleans which is on four CDs, an artist profile, and various awards and honorary degrees.
  - CV, circa 2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Robert Kipniss Radio Interview With WWNO 3-13-2006, New Orleans", circa 2006; Archival Resource Key; 4 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Artist Profile, circa 2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Blackton Family tree, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Awards, circa 1995-2021; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Honorary Degrees, circa 1979-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, circa 1989-2017; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; .2 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence is professional and personal in nature and is with The British Museum, Robin Magowan, William Kinnison, and others.
  - Correspondence (1980s), circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence (1990s), circa 1993-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence (2000s), circa 2000-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence (2000s), circa 2010-2017; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Undated Correspondence, circa 1989-2017; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The British Museum, circa 1994-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Kendy Genovese, circa 2009-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Leslie Van Breen, circa 2012-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Myrna Hayutin, circa 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Pam Wurzer, circa 2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Robin Magowan, circa 2010-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - William Kinnison, circa 2011-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Cards, circa 1990-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Writings, circa 1954-2017; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; .2 Linear feet Box 1
  Writings include poems and personal writings by Kipniss as well as the manuscript for Shine (2017), a novella by Kipniss.
  - "German Symbolist Painters of the Nineteenth Century", Thesis, circa 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Shine (2017) by Robert Kipniss, Manuscript, circa 2017; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Artist Statements, circa 1999-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Personal Writings, circa 2000-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Printed Materials, circa 1952-2023; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 1.9 Linear feet Boxes 1, 2, 4, and 5
  Printed material includes exhibition catalogs and announcements, scrapbooks, a DVD for the exhibition Whispering Light FWMIA Exhibition (2016) and a CD for the exhibition Seen In Solitude: Robert Kipniss Prints From The James F. White Collection (2006). Also included are news clippings and various art publications.
  - Exhibition Announcements (1970s), circa 1975-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Exhibition Announcements (1980s), circa 1980-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Exhibition Announcements (1990s), circa 1990-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Exhibition Announcements (2000s), circa 2000-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Exhibition Announcements (2000s), circa 2013-2023; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Undated Exhibition Announcements, circa 1975-2023; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (1950s), circa 1952-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (1960s), circa 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (1970s), circa 1971-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (1980s), circa 1980-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (1990s), circa 1991-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (1990s), circa 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (2000s), circa 2000-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (2000s), circa 2006-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (2000s), circa 2010-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Catalogs (2000s), circa 2015-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Undated Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1952-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Chase Gallery, Clippings Scrapbook, circa 1976-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - New Orleans Museum of Art, circa 2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Seen In Solitude: Robert Kipniss Prints From The James F. White Collection", circa 2006; Archival Resource Key; 1 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - South Africa, Clippings and Exhibition Materials, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Whispering Light FWMIA Exhibition PSA DVD", circa 2016; Archival Resource Key; 1 Electronic discs (DVD) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Art Publications, Archival Resource Key
    - Art Magazines, circa 1958-2023; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Art Publications, circa 1958-2023; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
    - Monthly Art Journals, circa 1972-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - Artwork Reviews, circa 1975-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Magazine Clippings, circa 1966-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - News Clippings, circa 1952-2023; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
  - News Clippings, circa 1952-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - News Clippings, Scrapbook, circa 1952-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Letterhead, circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1973-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, circa 1987-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Photographic Materials, circa 1932-2007; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; .8 Linear feet Boxes 3, 5, and 6
  Photographic material includes photographs of Kipniss, of his artwork, and of his exhibitions.
  - Robert Kipniss, circa 1932-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Century Club, circa 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Drawings For Show At Tyler Museum, Tyler, TX, circa 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition At The Century Association In The President's Room, Negatives, circa 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition At The Wichita Falls Museum Of Art, circa 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Pencil Drawings, Photographs, circa 1998-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Exhibition at ACME, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Exhibition, Butler Institute of American Art, Negatives, circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Society of American Graphic Artists (SAGA) Award Dinner, circa 2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 60's Days, circa 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Photograph Album, circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1969-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11-13)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1969-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Negatives, circa 1969-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 2-3)